(upbeat music)
- We will now discuss
the concept of utility.
Utility is a very, very
important concept in economics
and it only adds, it only...
For us to be able to talk about utility,
we only need to add one
additional assumption
in our preference, on
our preference relations
and that assumption is called continuity.
We're not gonna get into the details
of this this assumption,
this technical assumption of continuity
but we will give the idea,
we will provide the idea
behind this assumption.
The idea is that if you
have two bundles, A and B,
and bundle A is strictly preferred to B,
so A is preferred over B,
then small changes, or small
enough changes or variations,
alterations to these bundles
will respect the ordering.
So I can have a small
enough change in A or in B,
and the order of this preference,
meaning A preferred to
B will still remain.
So let's start with defining
this utility and utility function.
Please pay careful
attention to this point,
because it's a crucial concept
and it's always simpler
than it sounds, okay?
So utility is nothing,
but what we also call
a satisfaction level.
Satisfaction level equals utility, okay?
How happy, how satisfied,
how enjoyable a consumption,
the consumption of some
bundle is for the consumer.
That is a utility level.
How many utils this bundle,
this supermarket card gives the consumer.
And the utility function
is just an extension
or a way to extend this concept
to represent a whole array
of satisfaction levels
for each of the possible options
the consumer might have, okay?
So for example, utility level,
as we were saying, the idea of utility
and the utility function
is that people assign different bundles
or different consumption options
to a satisfaction level, right?
I might feel as happy as 100
with one supermarket card
and I might feel as happy as 90
with another supermarket card.
So those numbers 100
and 90 would be for me
the satisfaction levels or utility levels.
But to be able to work with utility
we need to learn a little bit
of additional notation and math,
and that is what we're going to do here.
In the past, with preference relations,
we said that a bundle,
for example, in this case
one iPhone and zero Galaxy,
which is the bundle on the left,
is strictly preferred
to the Galaxy 8 bundle
which is zero iPhones and one Galaxy 8.
I need to update this slides
for newer versions, by the way.
Anyway, but that was what we did before,
iPhone strictly preferred to Galaxy 8.
Now we're gonna write it in this way,
the utility of iPhone 7
greater than the utility of Galaxy 8.
So you see there is similarity
between this way of writing,
the same thing as this is,
these two things are,
they mean the same thing,
that iPhone 7 is better for
this person than Galaxy 8,
that iPhone 7 is strictly
preferred in this case
and the utility level of
iPhone 7 is strictly greater
in this case, they mean the same.
But because we want to do
this for the commodity space,
we need to use, you know, the
two entries of each bundle.
For example, in this case,
each bundle is between beer and pizza.
So the bundle, two beers, three pizzas,
is strictly preferred to the bundle
one beer and four pizzas.
So this guy prefers
two beers, three pizzas
over one beer, four pizzas.
Instead of writing in
this preference manner,
we will now write in this utility format,
which is the utility of 2,3
greater than the utility of 1,4.
You might be thinking,
"Wait, but we already
learned preference relations
and they were talking
about something similar
about people preferring
some bundles over others."
And you're right, however,
there is a connection
and there is a reason why
we want to use utility.
The connection is the following.
If the consumer preference relations
that we have discussed in the past
satisfy this assumption's completeness,
transitivity, continuity,
then whatever preference
relations that we have seen
or we have assumed for a consumer
can be represented by a
continuous utility function, okay?
So what that means is that
as long as (mumbles) we,
as long as we are
assuming that preferences,
that the consumer satisfies completeness,
transitivity and continuity,
then we don't need to really worry about
describing this consumer's preferences
in terms of preference relations
with the squiggly symbols,
we can simply use utility functions,
which is what we're going to do next.
In formal terms this equivalence
or this representation
of preference relations, the symbols,
the squiggly symbols,
and utility functions,
we need to be sure we
understand what is the formal
or logical and mathematical connection.
So, we say option or bundle X'
is strictly preferred to bundle X",
if and only if the utility level of X'
is greater than the utility level of X",
regardless or for any pair of X' and X".
And the same thing should
be true for week preference,
If we say that X' is
weekly preferred to X",
that should happen if and only if
the utility level of X' is greater than,
is equal or greater than
the utility level of X".
And this is similar for indifference,
if X' is indifferent to X",
that should happen even not
if the utility level of X'
is equal to the utility level of X", okay?
So if these three things are true,
then it must be that the utility
function, whatever that is,
it is representing the
same ranking of preference
of all possible options,
and therefore is representing
the same preference relations,
it is representing the same brain
of the consumer, in a sense.
What do we mean when we say
that the utilities also
representing preferences?
Let's just provide some examples.
Suppose some bundle X gives
a satisfaction level of six
and some bundle Y gives
satisfaction level of two,
then because of that satisfaction level
six for X and two for Y, we
know that it must be that X,
that bundle X is strictly
preferred than bundle Y,
but we know that because
six is greater and two
but we can say that X is
three times as preferred as Y,
and the reason is that bundles are,
or sorry, utility are subjective numbers,
those are numbers or satisfaction levels
that are defined at the
individual consumer levels,
they cannot be compare across consumers.
I mean, I can choose to call my top choice
satisfaction level 10,
and maybe you would choose
to call your top satisfaction level 100.
It doesn't matter, what matters to us
is the order that those
options, those bundles,
those supermarket cards have for us,
but doesn't, I cannot, I don't
know if what you call nine
is for me also nine or maybe a 80,
that comparison, that
interpersonal comparison
is not possible.
And that is why we say
utility is an ordinal concept,
although it takes some real number,
real values, real number values.
What really matters in utility,
it's how those satisfaction levels
order the options, rank
the order, the options,
not necessarily that when
I say utility level six
it's exactly six, because six
is a subjective assessment
that has to be consistent for
myself, not across consumers.
There is also very important connection
between utility function
and indifference curves.
Remember that an indifference curve
contains equally preferred bundles,
but since an indifference curve
that means that an indifference
curve can be defined
by all the bundles, all the options
whose utility levels are the same,
meaning that satisfy all these conditions
at any two points that belong
to the same indifference curve,
which will satisfy this
property that has to happen,
that also their utility
levels are the same.
In technical terms, this
implies that indifference curves
are actually contour curves,
contour level curves,
or just level curves for
the utility functions, okay?
What do we mean by that?
Well, you might have seen that some maps
will represent different altitude levels
by some lines around a,
for example, a hill
where the farthest most
or highest point, sorry,
it's in the middle and lower levels
or lower altitude points,
belong to contra curves
that are of course farther
away from the peak.
It is similar for indifference curves,
in difference curves we
will have that some lines,
some curves will denote
higher level of satisfactions
instead of higher altitude,
and other curves will denote
or will be associated with
lower levels of satisfaction
as opposed to lower altitude.
This is more precisely what you will see
in indifference curves.
For example, this is the
first utility function
we will describe.
This is one of the simplest one,
it's simply the
multiplication of x1 and x2.
And this utility function will
generate indifference curves
like the one you're seeing here.
This indifference curves are,
have this convex shape,
and in this particular graph or figure
we are only showing two of them, okay?
But we could also have
more of them if we had to,
in this case iT's enough
for us to have only two.
Sometimes we will need to indeed draw
more indifference curves in
the same figure or graph,
and that will allow us
to have a more clear
or more full description,
fuller description,
of the consumer's preferences.
We call the collection of
few indifference curves,
as we denote the collection
of few indifference curves
as an indifference map,
in the same way we were calling
sometimes altitude curves
as part of a map we will
say like few altitude
or satisfaction level
curves, indifference curves,
a indifference map in the same sense.
Next, we will describe or present the idea
that utility functions are not unique.
That is even, if the consumer is unique,
if the consumer has preferences
that are unlike any other consumers,
the utility function that
represents those preferences
is never unique.
So to understand why,
let's see first one important definition
which is the one of the
increasing function.
So from now on we will sometimes
do something like this,
we're gonna call it a memory bubble, okay?
So we were gonna say a
function X of whatever,
let's call it actually Z is increasing.
If every time you have a larger number,
the function, the value of the function
and the larger number is also larger
than the value of the function
in the smaller number.
If this is true, then we say
that F is increasing, okay?
So with this in mind,
we will say that any
two of the functions, U,
let me see if I can, okay, U and V.
Any two functions U or V
will represent the same preferences in one
if one, if I could write
one of them, let's say V,
by writing or by applying
a strictly increasing function on U, okay?
In other words, if I
can write V as F of U,
where F is strictly increasing
as we have just described on the iPad.
Let's see an example.
Suppose we go back to this utility
which is just a
multiplication of x1 and x2,
and we have three
bundles, 4,1, 2,3 and 2,2.
Under this utility function,
the utility of 2,3,
it will be the multiplication
which is 2 x 3,
six will be higher than
the utility of bundle 4,1,
which is 4 x 1, (mumbles),
and also the utility of bundle 2,2
because 2 x 2 is also 4, okay?
So in this case bundle
2,3 will be ranked up
and then 4,1 and 2,2 will be ranked next,
and between them wIll have
the same utility level,
meaning they will be indifferent,
the consumer will be
indifferent between those two.
And preference relation
terminology or notation,
this would be true, okay?
But we're gonna see
that this function here,
x1 x x2 is not the only function
that can represent those preferences.
For example, let's
consider V equals U square.
If V equals U square, we
will need to denote V,
the utility function V, as U
which was just x1 x x2 squared,
meaning the last, at the
end this utility function
will become simply x1 square x x2 square.
If you apply, if you calculate
the satisfaction level
through this new utility
function, x1 square x x2 square,
you will realize or we will find out
that the utility of 2,3 is 3,6 now
and the utility of 4,1
as well as the utility of 2,2 are both 16.
So the same ranking,
the exact same ordering as before emerges.
And that is because simply in the region
of positive utility, which
is what we're having before
because we are using only
positive x1 and positive x2,
x square is, sorry, the square function
is strictly increasing
in that positive region,
therefore, when we said V equals U square
we we're just apply an
increasing function,
and therefore the
ordering, as we have seen,
for whatever reordering
of whatever set of bundles
will be kept between U and V.
In this case, we just did
example with three bundles.
All right, so they do
represent the same preferences,
and that is because V will
preserve the same ordering as U,
given that it's only an
increase in transformation of U,
and therefore because it represents,
it reserves the same ordering
as we have seen before,
it must be then that it represents
also the same preferences.
Here's another transformation,
in this case is W,
W is 2 x U + 10.
Is that an increase in transformation?
Yes, because 2 x U is an
increased transformation
so 2 x U + 10, it is indeed
an increased transformation.
We can apply the same
thing, the same logic,
and we'll find out that,
again, W also keeps the same order in,
and therefore W also represents
the same preferences as U, okay?
(upbeat music)